Guide to the Individual manuscripts, publications, and artifacts, 150 AD. - 2014 MS2135
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Individual manuscripts, typescripts, artifacts, and images, MS2135 Series 1
  - Field catalogue of transit stars, 1870 ca. (Box 9, Folder 107)
    George Davidson, a geographer and astronomer, worked for the U.S. Coast Survey, 1845-1895, and was in charge in 1850 of making an accurate survey of the Pacific coast to meet the needs of navigation. William Healey Dall (1845-1927) was a naturalist who also worked for the U.S. Coast Survey, 1871-1884. Title from cover. The ms. is apparently a transcript of Davidson's Field catalogue of 983 transit stars. Washington: Govt. Print. Off., 1874. Front free endpaper has two inscriptions: "Copied from Prof. Davidson's Ms. List July 10-17, 1871, San Francisco, Cal." and "Property of W.H. Dall". Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 4.
  - George Washington, portrait, undated (Box 8, Folder 108)
    Text with portrait. "Engraved by W. Humphreys. WASHINGTON. From a Picture by gilbert stewart in the posession of T. B. Barklay Esq. of Liverpool. Under the Superintendance of the Society of the Diffusion of Useful Knowledge. London Published by Charles Knight. Ludgate Street." "With the Compliments of Stephen Joel Trachtenberg President The George Washington University Washington DC" Formerly ACC#689. Received by the University Archives in April 1998.
  - Autograph book, 1883-1884 (Box 11, Folder 109)
    J. B. McCarthy was Washington correspondent of the San Francisco chronicle, published by M.H. De Young. The volume contains autographs of Washington correspondents of American newspapers, and some U.S. Senators. Gift of Wood Gray, 1968. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 67.
  - John Quincy Adams, undated (Box 11, Folder 110)
    A signed photograph of John Quincy Adams (11 x 7 cm.) and a signature frank of his from a letter to John Marston. Anonymous gift in 1950. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 16.
  - Memory book, 1822-1830 (Box 11, Folder 111)
    Emily Marston was the daughter of John Marston, patriot of the American Revolution. Memory book of this young woman contains chiefly holograph signed entries, expressing good wishes toward her, or giving advice, sometimes in a poetic or allegorical form, about conduct of life. Contains entries by members of her family, and friends, including William Staughton, Thomas B. Adams, and John Adams (signed by him only), and others. Anonymous gift, 1950. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 16.
  - Oral history interview, 11/16/1986 (Box 11, Folder 119)
    Interview with Howard Gillette, Jr. of the American Studies Program of George Washington University. Discusses his career in governmental posts and his role in Democratic party politics in the District of Columbia. Interview done by Tilford Dudley a public affairs attorney. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 62. Gift of Tilford E. Dudley, 1986?
  - Portraits of George Washington, 1863-1910 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    Scrapbook of portraits of George Washington. Twenty portraits including engravings and portraits cut from periodicals and books. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 105 ff.
  - Ulysses S. Grant manuscript sheet from personal memoirs, 1885 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    This is a sheet from ms. of Personal memoirs of Gen. U.S. Grant in his own handwriting. Grant mentions his son Frederick Dent Grant's presence at the Battle of Port Gibson. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 65 f.
  - Samuel Blodget property ledger, 1880 ca.-1889 (Box 12, Folder 114)
    A complete discussion of this ms. appears in: The one millionth volume of the Gelman Library / David S. Zeidberg. Washington, D.C.: The George Washington University, 1984. Samuel Blodget, a merchant and architect, invested heavily in early Washington real estate. He died intestate, leaving his estate in litigation. This ms. ledger book, in several hands, is the work of Blodget descendents and their agents in an attempt to establish correct order of transfer of his property. P. 32-34 are by William F. Boogher (last date 1885). There is a ms. document tipped in the inside front cover, and 3 ms. documents laid inside the back cover. Gift of Albert H. Small, 1984. The official One Millionth Volume of the Gelman Library. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 14.
  - I heard Lincoln that day, 02/14/1938 (Box 12, Folder 115)
    This record album was donated by Professor, David Grier. Note with the record: "We are confident that you will not only enjoy but appreciate this unusual record. The original recording was made while Mr. Rathvon was speaking over short wave at the studios of WRUL. At that time the technique of reproducing the human voice under such circumstances was still in the experimental stage. Consequently imperfections unavoidably resulted and all of them could not be eliminated in this long-playing record, hence some fading and background noises in the latter part. Mr. Rathvon was a boy of nine when he heard Abraham Lincoln give this immortal address." The record says "Copied from orignal narration as recorded February 12, 1938."
  - Cartoon, undated (Map-folder 13, Folder 116)
    W. A. Rogers was a political cartoonist during the late 1800s and early 1900s. Many of his cartoons appeared in Harper's Weekly. This item is a political cartoon by W.A. Rogers in the "Washington Post."
    Formerly ACC#551
  - Cartoon, 1960 ca. (Map-folder 13, Folder 117)
    James T. Berryman (1902-1971) was the son of Clifford K. Berryman (1869-1949). James T. Berryman won the Pulitzer prize in 1950 for his cartoon, "All Set for a Super-Secret Session in Washington." This is one sheet with two political cartoons by James Berryman. They were printed in the "Washington Star." One cartoon dealt with President Johnson and is autographed. ca. 1960s
    Oversize folder: Formerly ACC#550
  - The principles of the design of steel bridges, 1960 ca. (Box 14)
    Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 74 f
  - Bibliography of children's books set in Washington, D.C., 1986 (Box 15, Folder 120)
    Paper written for a course on the history of Washington, D.C. at George Washington University: A bibliography of children's books set in Washington, D.C., and Language and subject in children's literature set in Washington, D.C. Gift in 1986 of Howard Gillette. Formerly Ind. Ms.Bd. 53
  - Coffee talk: the creation of gay space in a Washington coffeehouse, 05/01/1997 (Box 15, Folder 121)
    A senior paper produced at George Washington University. Ethnography of Pop Stop, a tea and coffee house at 1513 Seventeenth Street, N.W., Washington, D.C. Possibly a gift of Howard Gillette in 1997.
  - The Future of the District of Columbia Reunion with Maryland a Just and Practical Solution, 03/28/1996 (Box 15, Folder 122)
  - A DC Neighborhood by the Anacostia River: Kenilworth, 1701-2005 (Box 15, Folder 123)
  - Federal Schoolmen's Club, records, 1923-1959 (Box 15, Folder 124)
  - Story of the Heights: Massachusetts Avenue Heights, Washington D.C., 1911 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - The business and personal letter book of Edward T. McLean, Secretary-Treasurer of the Washington Post, 05/06/1909-04/09/1910 (Box 18, Folder 125)
    Contains carbon copies of letters McLean wrote, chiefly about Washington Post business. Formerly call# PN 4874 .M38 M38 f Gift of Bartholomew Cox
  - A Female Modernist in the Classical Capital: Chloethiel Woodward Smith and The Architecture of Southwest Washington, DC, 2006 (Box 18, Folder 126)
  - U.S. Bond printed by Paul Revere and signed by George Washington, 01/17/1792 (Box 19, Folder 128)
    Octavo (8vo.), oblong; two (2) pages. Engraved by Paul Revere. Issued by the United States Loan-Office on behalf of the State of Virginia. Payable to "George Washington of the County of Fairfax.. ." [No. 353]. January 17, 1792 for "Two Hundred Fourty-seven dollars & ninety-eight cents, assuemd debt bearing interest at six per cent. per annum.. ."Endorsed on verso by Washington: "I request the within debt may be carried to my credit on the Books of the Treasury of the United States. October 1, 1794. G. Washington."
    Donated to Gelman Library by Sheldon Cohen.
  - Architectural drawings: 5126 Tilden Street, NW, Spring Valley, Washington, D.C., 1964 (Tube 20, Folder 129)
    These schematic drawings came in with the Charyk, papers, but were separated.
  - The Loyal Brother or The Persian Prince, 1911 (Box 21, Folder 130)
    A play on the Popish Plot Edited with introduction and notes by P. Hamelius.
  - Three speeches against continuing the army, &c.,: as they were spoken in the House of Commons the last session of Parliament: to which are added the reasons given by the Lords, who protested against the bill for punishing mutiny and desertion, 1718 (Box 21, Folder 131)
    2 copies
  - A letter ballancing the necessity of keeping a land-force in times of peace, with the dangers that may follow on it, 1697 (Box 21, Folder 132)
  - An argument, shewing that a standing army is inconsistent with a free government, and absolutely destructive to the constitution of the English monarchy, 1697 (Box 21, Folder 133)
  - An argument, shewing that a standing army is inconsistent with a free government, and absolutely destructive to the constitution of the English monarchy, 1697 (Box 21, Folder 134)
    Reprint from 1817
  - A discourse concerning militia's and standing armies with relation to the past and present governments of Europe and of England in particular, 1697 (Box 21, Folder 135)
  - A Letter to a Member of Parliament Concerning Guards and Garrisons, 1699 (Box 21, Folder 136)
  - Draconica, or, An abstract of all the penal laws touching matters of religion, and the several oaths and tests thereby enjoyned with brief observations thereupon, 1688 (Box 21, Folder 137)
  - The seaman's opinion of a standing army in England, in opposition to a fleet at sea, as the best security of this kingdom in a letter to a merchant, written by a sailor, 1699 (Box 21, Folder 138)
  - The last speech & behaviour of William, late Lord Russel, upon the scaffold in Lincolns-Inne-Fields, a little before his execution, on Saturday, July 21, 1683, 07/21/1683 (Box 21, Folder 139)
    being condemned for high-treason in conspiring the death of the King, and the subversion of the government &c.: together with the paper delivered by him to the sheriffs, and signed with his own hand: also the last speeches, behaviour, and prayers of Capt. Thomas Walcot, John Rouse Gent., & William Hone, joyner, a little before their execution at Tyburn, on Friday the 20th of July, 1683, being condemned for high-treason in conspiring &c.
  - The late Lord Russel's case with observations upon it, 1689 (Box 21, Folder 140)
    Written by the Honorable Henry Lord De la Mere
  - Tilden Gardens grounds committee records, 1959-1961 (Box 21, Folder 141)
    Constructed in the 1920s, Tilden Gardens is the first suburban-style apartments in Cleveland Park. The complex sits on a 5-acre triangular block on Connecticut Avenue. The architects based their cross-shaped floor plan for Tilden Gardens on Philadelphia's Alden Park. Designed by Parks & Baxter and Harry L. Edwards, these units opened between 1927 and 1930. The extensive landscaping of this sloping five-acre site was done by landscape architect Henry Bauer, with fountains, pools, pergolas, and terraces. Four buildings converted to co-op in 1939.
  - Tilden Gardens grounds committee records, 1961-1965 (Box 21, Folder 142)
  - Transportation Metro Alternate Subway Design, 1974-1975 (Box 25, Folder 144)
  - Columbia Heights and The George Washington University of Washington, D.C., 1907 (Box 25, Folder 145)
  - Lafayette Square, undated (Box 25, Folder 146)
    The folder contains a brochure and an envelope with photographic negatives
  - Park View, 1921 (Box 25, Folder 147)
    Directory and History of Park View
  - Watergate Hotel, 1972-1976 (Box 25, Folder 148)
    Folder includes a guest directory, a brochure, and a newsletter titled "Watergate Hotel Review"
  - A Brief History of Woodley, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 149)
    Woodley Hill is listed on the back of the brochure. The original folder title was Woodley Park.
  - Hotels and Motels in the Washington Area, 1958-1970 (Box 25, Folder 150)
    This folder contains brochures
  - Invitation to a dance from the Seven Bachelors of Beltsville to Philp Crossfield and Sisters, 09/03/1909 (Box 25, Folder 151)
  - Inauguration of the President of the United States program, 03/1917 (Box 25, Folder 152)
  - Prospectus of the Washington and University Railroad Company of the District of Columbia, undated (Box 25, Folder 153)
  - Tilden Gardens a plan and a map, 03/04/1930-10/16/1959 (Map-folder 26, Folder 143)
    This folder includes a 1930 map and a 1959 replanting survey and general recommendations
  - Chinatown, 1974-1982 (Box 29, Folder 154)
    This folder contains newsletters, flyers, and other promotional materials for Chinatown.
  - Shaw, 1971-1975 (Box 29, Folder 155)
    This folder contains slides, brochures, and a dedication for the Grace McCollough Canaanland Apartments.
  - Images of William Henry Schafer on the C and O Canal, undated (Box 29, Folder 156)
    From a letter with the images written by John B. Cole, grandson of William H. Schafer. "These photos are unidentified as to exact location, date, event, and men except for William Henry Schafer (1874-1950) lifelong Cumberland resident. There's a biographical sketch of him in History of Allegany Co. Md. by Thomas and Williams, 1923, Vol. II p.1083. In a column in Cumberland Times by Kay Stangel, Sat. Sept. _ 2000 there's mention of 'Motor Cabin Boats (on the canal) that would take a party down the canal to some shady groves where a picnic lunch would be served followed by a moon light return on the Canal'"
  - Shakespeare Club of Washington Minute book, 12/18/1880-04/26/1884 (Box 29, Folder 157)
  - 2001 Presidential Inauguration memorabilia [1/2] (Box 30, Folder 158)
    This folder includes an official guide book and a media guide. Formerly Ephemera Coll. #22.
  - 2001 Presidential Inauguration memorabilia [2/2] (Box 30, Folder 159)
    This folder includes a media guide, tickets, program, and invitations. Formerly Ephemera Coll. #22.
  - Bicentennial of the United States Senate, 1989-1990 (Box 30, Folder 160)
    This folder contains programs, ticket and a commeorative stamp. Formerly Ephemera Coll. #4.
  - Correspondence of Jeremiah Elkins, 1827-1829 (Box 30, Folder 161)
  - Catalogue of Stereoscopic, Cabinet and Large Views of Washington, undated (Box 30, Folder 164)
  - Major changes in our industry during my experience, 03/24/1998 (Box 30, Folder 167)
    Harry Baum gave a lecture to the students of professor Joe Jeff Goldblatt in 1998. At the time he was 87 years old and was one of the leaders in the European meetings industry. Professor Goldblatt requested a copy of the speech be preserved in Special Collections.
  - Million Man March flier, 10/16/1997 (Box 30, Folder 168)
  - Photograph album, undated (Box 30, Folder 169)
    The provenance of this album is unknown. It appears to be a family album with images of people, vacations and perhaps home. Many of the images do have brief descriptions, but the pencil has worn away and made it extremely difficult to read. For the descriptions written in pen here are some of the image captions: Lake George, the Sagamore Inn at Lake George, 30 Central Ave. in Newark, M.V. Cowles, Bellevue Hospital N.y.. City, Cornell University Medical College, Second Ave. N.y.. City, St. George's Church, Stuyvesant Square, N.y.., Hospital erected by J.P. Morgan, Stuyvesant Square, N.y.., Mary P. St. John. There are images of Washington D.C. including the Capitol, the Chinese Legation, the White House, and Corcoran Art Gallery.
  - Independence declared 1776 the union must be preserved, 1839 (Map-folder 31, Folder 162)
    Text on lithograph "The Columns are intended to represent New-England arising out of Old-England surmounted by Hope and Liberty. The View is that of the Battle of Bunker Hill, from Chelsea, with Boston seen in the distance. The main subject being General Washington surrounded by one Representative frm each of the thirteen States -- The National Flag of 1776, (a Pine Tree, on a white field), is on the right whilst the present one is seen on the left hand."
  - Abraham Lincoln: President of the United States. Assassinated April 14th, 1865 (Map-folder 31, Folder 163)
    From Worldcat catalog record "A facsimile of Lincoln's signature is above the title./ The border of the engraving consists of (clockwise): a stack of books resting on a flail and chain covered by the "Proclamation of Freedom;" a black family labeled Fugitives leaving their home; a personification of Peace in front of a fruitful landscape flanked by an eagle carrying a banner in its beak that reads "E Pluribus Unum;" two hands clasped in a handshake, one coming from a sheaf of wheat, the other from corn and cotton, over a banner reading "The Union Forever;" an allegorical figure of war in front of a desolate and burning landscape, carrying a sword and tattered flag and treading on a six-headed monster labeled Rebellion; and a white family labeled Patriots with a covered wagon./ The engraving was entered "according to act of Congress AD 1864 by J.C. Buttre in the Clerk's office of the District Court of the Southern District of New York"
    The photograph by M.B. Brady; border design by W. Momberger; engraving by J.C. Buttre
  - Council of the District of Columbia Resolution: James Forman Recognition Resolution of 2001, 10/02/2001 (Map-folder 31, Folder 165)
    Signed by Chairman of the Council Linda Cropp
  - Record of Cigar Manufacturers U.S. Internal Revenue Service, 1900-1902 (Flat box 32, Folder 166)
  - Pencil drawing, undated; Series 1; Perske, Martha (Oversize-folder 1, Item 1)
    Biography
    Martha Perske is a self-taught illustrator who produces pencil drawings of people with disabilities. Martha Perske's work has been recognized by most of the major disability organizations in the Western world. She illustrated major reports on mental retardation for Presidents Nixon and Carter, designed the International Year of Disabled Persons commemorative stamp, and drew the persons with disabilities for Marlo Thomas's "Free to Be a Family." She was commissioned to present an autographed drawing to Diana, Princess of Wales, and she drew the illustration for an attitude-change campaign jointly sponsored by Johnson & Johnson and the Arc of the United States.
    Scope and Contents
    This is a pencil drawing of seven children with various disabilites. Some of the children are drawn with animals.
    Children with disabilities
  - Washington Cathedral Bells on day of arrival, 06/1963; Series 1 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - World War II postcard, Circa 1943; Series 1 (Box 33, Folder 11)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchased by Gelman Library, February 23, 2012 (2012.020)
    World War, 1939-1945; Churchill, Winston; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano); Stalin, Joseph
  - Plat maps University Urban Renewal Area, 1957 August 14 - September 19; Series 1 (Tube 1)
    General
    This tube consists of four plat drawings. Two have the designation Condition of Residential Structures, University Urban Renewal Area, District of Columbia Redevelopment Land Agency and are dated 9/19/1957 and two that have the designation Exhibit B Condition of Dwelling Units, District of Columbia Redevelopment Land Agency and are dated 8/14/1957.
    These were uncovered as part of a clean up effort in the University Archives. It is unknown how and when they arrived Special Collections.
  - Four 1901 manuscript letters of qualification from African American women seeking teaching positions for cooking in the Washington, DC school, Series 1; 4 item(s) (Box 33, Folder 12)
    Biographical / Historical
    These four letters were addressed to Emma S. Jacobs, Director of Domestic Service in Public Schools, in Washington, DC. Sent in the fall of 1901, these letters from four different women contain lists of their credentials, including what home economics and cooking science courses and programs they may have attended, what positions they have held recently, and the salaries paid for those positions.
    Schools -- Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Education; Black studies; African Americans; Jacobs, Emma S.
  - Family photo album of Mrs. H.B. Parker, mother-in-law of the Hon. David Jayne Hill, Ambassador to Germany, Holland, and Switzerland under President William Howard Taft, circa 1850 (Object 1)
    This photo album is approximately 6"x 4"x 3" and is emerald green. The word "Album" is written along the spine in gold, old style font. The album contains a notecard explaining that this album is the "family photo album of Mrs. H. B. Parker, Mother-in-Law of the Hon. David Jayne Hill, Ambassador to Germany, Holland, and Switzerland under President William Howard Taft."
    The album also contains two silk bookmarks. One is cream-colored and has "H.B. Parker 1851" stitched onto it. The other is blue with a cross stitched on it.
    There are 46 individual portraits in the album. The subjects are men and women of all ages, including multiple portraits of infants and young children. Some have been hand-colored. Each portrait is matted on its own page. None of the photographs are labeled or dated.
    These photographs are likely albumen prints because of their sepia tone and glossy finish. Albumen professional portraits such as these were called carte de visites (CDVs), a style of photograph invented in 1854 which became wildly popular around 1860. CDVs were traded amongst friends and family and acted as calling cards.
  - Suffrage Parade postcards, 1913 March 3; Series 1 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified image of a man drawn by James King, undated; Series 1 (Oversize-folder 2)
  - George Wilt Spangler and Acacia fraternity image, Circa 1923-1930; Series 1 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    A letter that came with the image from Robin Richardson (Spangler's step daughter-in-law) provides the following data: "The person at the far right, front row is George Wilt Spangler, my step father-in-law, who completed George Washington Law School and perhaps also obtained his undergraduate degree there. He was President of Acacia fraternity. George died at age 80 in May, 1985 after a successful career as an attorney with the US Justice and State Departments and later in private practice. The photo was taken circa 1923 (age 18) to 1930 (age 25)."
    note with the file from the Alumni office lists Columbia College of Arts and Sciences BA 1927, Law JD 1933.
    The back of the image reads "The acacia house in Washington, D.C. where George lived several years and was president of his fraternity"
  - Thomas Brown, the 2nd District of Columbia Regiment, and the American Civil War, 2012 December 3; MS2135 Series 1 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    This is a senior thesis written by GW student Jared Johnson.
  - Images of Foggy Bottom, 1984-Circa 2009; Series 1; Winter, Richard; The images are all color and range in size from 3x5 to 4x6. (Box 35, Folder 1)
    These are images taken by the donor of his Foggy Bottom neighborhood and are primarily of buildings and street scenes. The area covered include M and 22nd and 23rd streets along with a small part of the Washington Circle. The majority of the images were taken by the donor looking out his balcony during construction of a large building. There are no images of the completed construction and thus is it uncertain which building is depicted. The dates are 1984 through Circa 2009.
    Gift of Richard Winter, April 12, 2013 (2013.009)
  - Night on Pennsylvania Avenue, Washington DC, undated; Series 1; Li Fu, Duoruo (Box 35, Folder 2)